<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The two covenants from Sinai, and Sion, drawn up catechetically, and plainly. Together with a briefe appendix, directing about the use of the new covenant in a practicall way. Published for the benefit especially of the inhabitants of Eastham, Essex. / By Samuel Slater.</title>
            <author>Slater, Samuel, d. 1704.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93323</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3978</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1185_1*</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204871</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864327</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864327</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116554</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93323)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116554)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 256:E1185[1*])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The two covenants from Sinai, and Sion, drawn up catechetically, and plainly. Together with a briefe appendix, directing about the use of the new covenant in a practicall way. Published for the benefit especially of the inhabitants of Eastham, Essex. / By Samuel Slater.</title>
                  <author>Slater, Samuel, d. 1704.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M.S. for Henry Overton in Popes head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf bears a permission to print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Covenant theology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116554:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE TWO
COVENANTS
From <hi>Sinai,</hi> and <hi>Sion,</hi>
drawn up Catechetically,
and plainly.</p>
            <p>Together with a briefe Appen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dix,
directing about the uſe of the
<hi>New Covenant in a practicall way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Publiſhed for the benefit eſpecially
of the Inhabitants of <hi>Eaſtham,</hi> Eſſex.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>SAMUEL SLATER.</hi>
            </p>
            <bibl>Hebrews 12. 18, 19, 22, 23.</bibl>
            <q>Yee are not come unto the Mount that might be tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched,
and that burned with fire, nor unto blackneſſe,
and darkneſſe, and tempeſt, and the ſound of a Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet,
&amp;c. But yee are come unto Mount Sion, and to
the Citie of the living God, the heavenly Jeruſalem,
and to an innumerable company of Angels, to the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall
aſſembly, and Church of the firſt borne, which
are written in heaven, and to God the Judge of all,
and to the Spirits of juſt men made perfect, and to
Jeſus the Mediator of the New Covenant.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>
Printed by <hi>M. S.</hi> for <hi>Henry Overton</hi>
in <hi>Popes head</hi> Alley, 1644.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="Sinai and Sion" type="table_of_covenants">
            <pb facs="tcp:116554:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:116554:2"/>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Mount Sinai</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Mount Sion</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Was ſcituate in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
where the <hi>Iſraelites</hi>
were ſojourners, <hi>Exod.</hi> 19. 1.</cell>
                     <cell>Was ſcituate in <hi>Canaan,</hi>
where the <hi>Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>aelites</hi> were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritors,
and at <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ruſalem,</hi>
where God placed his Name,
2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Here <hi>Moſes</hi> ſtood as a Typi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
Mediator, <hi>Exod.</hi> 24. 12.</cell>
                     <cell>He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e Chriſt ſtands as the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator
of the New Teſtament,
<hi>Rev.</hi> 14 1. <hi>Heb</hi> 12.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Here a fiery Law was pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed,
and given in charge,
<hi>Deut.</hi> 33. 2.</cell>
                     <cell>Here the joyfull ſound of the
Goſpel is heard, <hi>Pſal. 89. I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa.</hi>
40. 9.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Here the Law was written
in Tables of ſtone by the finger
of God, <hi>Exod.</hi> 31. 18.</cell>
                     <cell>Here the Law is written in
the fleſhly Tables of the heart,
by the Spirit of the living God,
2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3 3.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Here was blackneſſe, and
darkneſſe, and Tempeſt, <hi>Heb.</hi>
12 18.</cell>
                     <cell>Here is brightneſſe, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
on of beautie, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. 2.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Here matters were mannaged
viſibly, and to the outward
ſences, <hi>Exod.</hi> 10. 18.</cell>
                     <cell>Here m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tters are mannaged
after a more ſpirituall manner,
2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 8.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Here <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the people
did exceed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ngly feare, and quake,
<hi>Exod. 20. Heb.</hi> 12. 21.</cell>
                     <cell>Here m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n have boldneſſe, and
confidence towards God, <hi>Heb.</hi>
10. 19.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Here was a gendring to Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,
<hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 24.</cell>
                     <cell>Here men are called to a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
libertie, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 13.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Here was the miniſtration of
condemnation, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.</cell>
                     <cell>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>re is the miniſtration of
r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ghteouſneſſe, and life, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <bibl>PSAL. 87. 5.</bibl>
               <q>Of Sion it ſhall be ſaid, this, and that man was borne
in her, and the Higheſt himſelfe ſhall eſtabliſh her.</q>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:116554:3"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath pleaſed the Father of lights,
out of tender compaſſion to the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorne
poſteritie of <hi>Adam,</hi> over which
the Prince of darkneſſe hath drawne
a black vaile of ignorance, to ingage
the promiſe for the deſtroying of that Vaile, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving
the face of the covering ſpread over all
Nations, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25. 7. That ſo Men may with open
face, behold, as in a Glaſſe, the glory of God, and
be transformed into his Image from glory to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 18. Which promiſe as it is to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed
by Faith, and ſued out by prayer, ſo it is to
be ſerved, in order to its accompliſhment by the
faithfull end<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>avours of all Chriſts ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rvants in the
Miniſtery, that ſo poore ſoules that have lived
long under ſhadows, and walked in darkneſſe,
may be brought into marveilous light, and not
goe to bed in the darke, and ſo lie downe in eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
ſorrow. For which cauſe, the Author hath
been mooved to preſent theſe few pages to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique
view, in hope, that ſome may make advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage
of them, for the nnderſtanding of the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries
of God. Which if any ſhall, he hath his
aime, who counts it one of the greateſt comforts
of his life, to be any way uſefull to the Church
of God, and Children of the Covenant.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="Scriptural_quotations">
            <pb facs="tcp:116554:3"/>
            <head>Some ſelect Scriptures propund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
to promote an endeavour in
people after Knowledge.</head>
            <q>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Deſired knowledge of God more than
burnt offerings, <bibl>
                  <hi>Hoſea</hi> 6. 6.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>The Lord hath a controverſie with the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants
of the Land, becauſe there is no know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
of God, <bibl>
                  <hi>Hoſea</hi> 4. 1.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Some have not the knowledge of God, I ſpeake
this to your ſhame, <bibl>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>My people are deſtroyed for lacke of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
<bibl>
                  <hi>Hoſea</hi> 4. 6.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>How long yee ſimple ones will yee love ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie,
and fooles hate knowledge, <bibl>
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 1. 22.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>When Wiſdome entreth into thy heart, and
knowledge is pleaſant to thy ſoule, diſcretion ſhall
preſerve thee, underſtanding ſhall keepe thee, <bibl>
                  <hi>Pro.</hi>
2. 16.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Therefore be yee not unwiſe, but underſtanding
what the will of the Lord is, <bibl>
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. 17.</bibl>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="propositions">
            <pb facs="tcp:116554:4"/>
            <head>Some generall Propoſitions, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending
the ſumme of that Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,
which is neceſſary to be
knowne to Salvation.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD is an infinite and incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible
Spirit, having his beeing
of himſelfe, and all perfections
in himſelfe, in the unitie of whoſe
eſſence, wee are to acknowledge a Trinitie
of perſons, <hi>viz.</hi> the Father, the Sonne, and
the Holy Ghoſt, <bibl>
                  <hi>Joh. 4. 24. 1 Kings</hi> 8. 17.
1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 7.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>God in relation to man, as his creature, is
to be acknowledged of us, as a moſt wiſe,
powerfull, and glorious Creator, <bibl>
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>God with reſpect to man as a ſinner, is
to be acknowledged as a moſt wiſe, juſt,
mercifull, and gracious Redeemer, <bibl>
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.
6. Eſa. 43. 14.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>Man before his fall, was a creature of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable
excellencies, and ſingular privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges,
<pb facs="tcp:116554:4"/>
but not priviledged from falling,
<bibl>
                  <hi>Gen. 1. 31. Col. 3. 10. Eccleſ</hi> 7. 29.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>Man ſince the fall, is a creature extreame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
miſerable, but yet ſtanding under a poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie
of riſing, <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 7. 24. Hoſea</hi> 13. 9. &amp; 14.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>That helpe, which is provided for man,
in order to his riſing, is laid upon one that
is mightie, even Jeſus Chriſt, who is both
God, and man, a perſon choſen of his Father
to doe him ſervice, in working mans Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
and is for that purpoſe made unto us,
wiſdome, righteouſneſſe, ſanctification, and
redemption, <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 89. 19. Eſa. 9. 6. 7. Eſa.</hi> 42.
1. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 30.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>Jeſus Chriſt, and all bleſſings in, and
through him, are ours by beleeving, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,
firſt, there is a looking to Jeſus; ſecondly,
a leaning upon him; thirdly, an imbracing of
him; fourthly, a kiſſing of him; fiftly, a feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
upon him; ſixtly, a taking hold of him;
ſeventhly, a receiving of him; eightly a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
to him: all which are to be ſpiritually
underſtood, and ſpiritually to be performed,
<bibl>
                  <hi>Epheſ. 3. 17. Heb. 12. 2. Cant. 1. Heb.</hi> 11. 13.
<hi>Pſal. 2. 12. Joh. 6. Eſa. 27. 5. Joh.</hi> 1. 12.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>The ſoule is brought to beleeve, and ſo
to the fellowſhip of Chriſt, and bleſſings
<pb facs="tcp:116554:5"/>
through him, by the hearing of the Goſpel,
which is a doctrine of free grace, declaring
unto us that God is in Chriſt, reconciling the
world unto himſelfe, <bibl>
                  <hi>Joh. 6. Rom.</hi> 10. 14, 15.
17. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 19.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>That Goſpel, which is the grace of God
bringing ſalvation to ſuch as beleeve, doth
likewiſe teach men to deny ungodlineſſe, and
worldly luſts, and to live oberly, righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
and godly in this preſent world, <bibl>
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.
11, 12.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>Such as doe beleeve, and ſhew forth their
beleeving, by walking in newneſſe of life,
are juſtified from ſinne, paſſed from death to
life, and ſhall have after death a reſurrection
to eternall glory, <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 5. 1. Joh. 6. 36. Joh.</hi>
11. 26. <hi>Joh.</hi> 6. 44.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>Such as continue in ſinne, neglecting Chriſt,
and Goſpel mercies, ſhew themſelves to be
children of wrath, in bondage to Satan, and
ſo continuing, ſhall after death be raiſed up
to eternall ſhame, <bibl>
                  <hi>Joh. 3. 36. Epheſ. 2. 2 Tim.</hi>
2. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </p>
            <p>It is mens dutie, not to take matters delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
unto them, upon truſt, but to ſearch the
Scriptures, whether the things which they
reade, or heare be ſo, <bibl>
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 39.</bibl>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb facs="tcp:116554:5"/>
            <head>The two COVENANTS
from Sinai, and Sion.</head>
            <div type="question">
               <head>Queſtion.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N what way hath it ſeemed good to the
wiſdome of God, to deale with the
ſonnes of men in order to his glory, and
their happineſſe?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>Gods dealing with them both before, and
ſince the fall, hath been ordered out in a
way of Covenanting, <bibl>
                     <hi>Gen. 2. 16. Jere.</hi> 31, 32.
<hi>Ezek.</hi> 20. 37.</bibl>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="questions">
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What Covenant did God make with man
before his fall?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A Covenant of Workes, the ſumme
whereof is contained in the ten Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Levit. 18. 5. Gal.</hi> 3. 12.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What did this Covenant binde man unto?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To the performance of perfect obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
and that perpetually, <bibl>
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 27. 26.
<hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 10.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:116554:6"/>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Had man abilitie to performe what this
Covenant bound him to?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Sufficient abilitie there was given to
him, to performe whatſoever the Law re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7. 29.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What did that Covenant leade man to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect
from God, as the reward of his obedience?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A bleſſed life, in conſtant fellowſhip
with him, and ſweet fruition of him. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 12.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Was man ſtedfaſt in this Covenant?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Nothing leſſe, for he diſobeyed Gods
expreſſe command in eating the forbidden
fruit, and ſo became guiltie of breach of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Gen. 3. Eccleſ.</hi> 7. 29.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What condition hath man now brought
himſelfe into, through this breach of Covenant?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Into a moſt miſerable condition of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe,
impotency, guilt, and wrath, and
lyes open to the curſe of the Law, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
condemnation, <bibl>
                     <hi>Joh</hi> 15. 16.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Is there no helpe for man now lying under
this woefull condition?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No helpe at all by the Covenant he
hath broken, which doth ſtrictly require, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
obedience, or ſatisfaction, in caſe of
tranſgreſſion, without giving any power, or
ſhewing any mercy, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:116554:6"/>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Hath man no power to helpe himſelfe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He is altogether without ſtrength, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
to performe obedience, or make ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
either to repaire the wrong he hath
done to God, or the loſſe he hath ſuſtained
from himſelfe, <bibl>2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 5.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Is man then a creature altogether hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Not ſo, for God hath proclaimed his
Name to be mercifull, and gracious, <bibl>
                     <hi>Exod.</hi>
34. 6, 7.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How hath God ſhewed himſelfe ſo to be in
order to mans recovery?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By revealing a new Covenant, and ſo
bringing in a better and more bleſſed hope,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Jere. 31. 32. Heb.</hi> 8.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is that Covenant?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> A Covenant of free grace, and recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation
between himſelfe, and poore ſinners,
before alienated from him, and enemies to
him, <bibl>2 <hi>Cor. 5. 18, 19. Col.</hi> 1.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon what foundation is this Covenant
layd?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Not upon any abilitie in man, but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
Jeſus Chriſt, and his ſufficiency, upon
whom the Covenant is founded, and in whoſe
bloud it is eſtabliſhed, <bibl>
                     <hi>Eſa. 28. 16. 1 Pet.</hi> 2. 6.
<hi>Mat. 26. 28. Luk.</hi> 22. 20.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:116554:7"/>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Why doe you call it a new Covenant?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In two reſpects: firſt, in reſpect of the
Covenant of works, under which man was at
firſt planted: Secondly, In reſpect of that
difference, which is between the gracious
adminiſtrations under the old Teſtament,
and thoſe now undew the New.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Wherein doth that difference of admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations
conſiſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In ſundry particulars, whereof we will
mention but two, or three: Firſt, under the
old Teſtament, the Covenant was admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred
with a more rigorous exacting of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
to the morall Law, under the Goſpel
men are drawne to their dutie with more
ſweetneſſe: Secondly, Chriſt was then held
forth as one that was to come, but now as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
alreadie come: Thirdly, Chriſt, and the
bleſſing of the Covenant through him, were
then diſpenſed under carnall ordinances, and
cloudy Ceremonies, whereas now the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations
are more cleare, and ſpirituall, ſo
that wee may with open face behold, as in a
glaſſe, the glory of God in Jeſus Chriſt, <bibl>
                     <hi>Deut.</hi>
8. 1. <hi>&amp; 27. 26. Mat. 11. 28, 29. Rom.</hi> 12. 1.
<hi>Mal. 3. 1, 2. Heb. 9. 10. 1 Pet. 2. 9. 2 Cor.</hi>
3. 18.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:116554:7"/>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Was it not the ſame ſalvation, which was
then diſpenſed, that now the Goſpel brings, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
the difference of adminiſtration?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Vndoubtedly it was, Chriſt being the
ſame yeſterday, and to day, and for ever:
ſecondly, It being the ſame Spirit, and the
ſame faith, by which beleevers then were,
and now are made partakers of him, and of
all ſpirituall bleſſings in, and thorough him,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Heb. 13. 8. 2 Cor. 4. 13. Heb. 11. 1 Cor.</hi> 10.
3, 4.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> When did this Covenant take place?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Immediately after the fall, and it was
ſignified by that promiſe made to our firſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,
the ſeed of the woman ſhall breake the
Serpents head, being afterward confirmed to
<hi>Abraham,</hi> and to his ſeed, <bibl>
                     <hi>Gen. 3. 15. Gen.</hi> 15.
1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17. 1, 2.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Why then was the Law publiſhed after, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
mount Sinai?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Not as the ſtanding Covenant, nor to
diſanull the Covenant made and confirmed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
of God in Chriſt, but it was for mercifull
purpoſes, and the more to indeare the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe
of Grace to the heires thereof, <bibl>
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.
17, 18, 19.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is the matter of this new Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
under the Goſpel?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:116554:8"/>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Sure mercies, and ſweet promiſes,
which are all in Chriſt, yea, and in him A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Eſa. 55. 3. 2 Cor.</hi> 1. 20.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What are thoſe promiſes, and the mercies
conveyed by them?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That God will give a new heart, a heart
to know him, that he will write his law with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
us, put his feare into us, cauſe us to walke
in his ſtatutes, forgive our iniquities, cleanſe
us from our filthineſſe, be our God, and make
us his people, <bibl>
                     <hi>Ezek. 36. Jere.</hi> 31.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is required of ſuch as are taken into
this Covenant?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Nothing is required of them, but what
is given to them; It is required that men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve,
and repent, but it is freely given to
them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>; Mans dutie is the matter of
promiſe, as well as Gods mercy, <bibl>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 12.
<hi>Epheſ 2. 8. Phil. 1. 29. Act.</hi> 5. 31.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How then are men to deale with ſuch pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts
as require, that they beleeve, repent, and turne
to God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They are not to ſeeke ſtrength from
themſelves, but to ſearch into the Covenant,
and ſee what they can finde in the promiſe,
and ſo turne the promiſe into prayer. <hi>The
Appendix fully proves this.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:116554:8"/>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How will it ſtand with the juſtice of God
ſo highly offended, and requiring ſatisfaction, to
make ſuch a Covenant of grace and mercy?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Wee are to conſider this Covenant in
a reference of it to Jeſus Chriſt, as Mediator
thereof, undertaking to ſatisfie Gods ſtricteſt
juſtice, and to eſtate man in his richeſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,
in regard of whom, as alſo of Gods free
donation, it is a Teſtament, confirmed by the
death of the Teſtator, <bibl>
                     <hi>Heb. 12. 22, 23. Heb.</hi> 10.
<hi>Mat. 26. Heb.</hi> 8. 6.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Who is this Jeſus Chriſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The man, Gods-fellow, the Sonne of
the Father, but found in faſhion as a man, in
which eſtate he humbled himſelfe, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came
obedient to the death, even to the death
of the Croſſe, <bibl>
                     <hi>Zach. 13. 7. Phil.</hi> 2.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What followed upon his humbling him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
and being obedient to the death of the Croſſe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> His glorious exaltation, which is to be
conſidered in his reſurrection, aſcenſion, and
ſitting at Gods right hand, <bibl>
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 34, 35.
1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15, 11.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What did be ingage himſelfe to, as Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor
of this Covenant?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> He ingaged himſelfe to a three-fold of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,
Propheticall, Prieſtly, and Kingly, <bibl>
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 7.
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:116554:9"/>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What belongs to him to doe as a Prophet?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To reveale and make knowne the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,
therefore is he called the Angel and
Meſſenger of the Covenant, <bibl>
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 17.
<hi>Mal.</hi> 3. 1.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What was his buſineſſe as a Prieſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To make his Soule an offering for ſin,
and by the ſacrifice of himſelfe to God, to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
for us, and make ſure unto us, all the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings
of the Covenant, <bibl>
                     <hi>Eſa. 53. Heb.</hi> 10.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What belongs to him to doe as a King?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> To triumph over all guiltineſſe, by the
application of his bloud, to the conſciences of
his people, and to ſubdue all iniquitie, by the
efficacy of his grace, and ſo to erect and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter
a Kingdome in their hearts, ſtanding
in righteouſneſſe, peace, and joy in the Holy
Ghoſt, <bibl>
                     <hi>Heb. 9. &amp; 10. 18. Eſa. 52. Mich.</hi> 7.
15. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 17.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What proviſion is there made for the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication
of this Covenant to the ſonnes of men?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There is mercifull proviſion of means,
and that of two ſorts, firſt, outward, ſecondly,
inward.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What are the outward means?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, The miniſtration of the Word,
ſecondly, The holy Sacraments, <bibl>2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is done to the purpoſe of applying
<pb facs="tcp:116554:9"/>
this Covenant in the miniſtery?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The name of God, and of the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,
is proclaimed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and as an oyntment pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
forth, Chriſt with his bloud, and merits,
and all the benefits of his death, are openly
ſhewed, and ſignification made, that whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
will, may come and drinke of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
of life freely, <bibl>
                     <hi>Exod. 34. Cant. 1. Joh.</hi> 3.
14. <hi>Eſa. 55. 1. Rev.</hi> 22.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What are the Sacraments that belong to
this Covenant?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They are two, Baptiſme, and the Lords
Supper, wherein there are viſible Elements,
of Water in the one, and Bread and Wine in
the other; all Sacramentally holding forth
Chriſt, and ſerving to promote the applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of him, and all ſpirituall mercies through
him, <bibl>
                     <hi>Mat. 28. Mat.</hi> 26.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What doe theſe Sacraments eſpecially hold
forth concerning Chriſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> His ſacrifice and death, and ſo they hold
proportion with the Goſpel, which is a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
concerning Chriſt, and him crucified,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Rom. 6. 3. 1 Cor. 11. 26. 1 Cor.</hi> 1. 2.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How doe they ſerve, to promote the applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of Chriſt, and ſpirituall bleſſings by him?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They ſerve hereunto not onely by way
of ſignification, but alſo by way of obſignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb facs="tcp:116554:10"/>
and ſo are to be conſidered as Seales of
the Covenant, <bibl>
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 11.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is ſignified and ſealed in Baptiſme?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The death of Jeſus Chriſt, our union
with him, and intereſt in all the benefits by
him, particularly, remiſſion of ſinnes, and
ſanctification, <bibl>
                     <hi>Rom. 6. 4. Acts</hi> 2. 38.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is ſignified, and ſealed in the Lords
Supper?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Our continuance in the fellowſhip of
Chriſt, our living upon him, growing and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing
in him, who as he became a ſacrifice
to ſatisfie for ſinne, ſo is he become ſpirituall
meate, for the nouriſhment of our ſoules,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Titus 2. 5. Epheſ. 5. 2. John</hi> 6. 55.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Doe not the Sacraments ſerve to promote
the obedience that is to be performed under the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,
as well as the application of the mercies
thereof?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They ſerve ſtrongly to both purpoſes,
for as the application of the mercies is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered
by way of ſignification, and obſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
ſo is the performance of dutie furthered
by way of profeſſion and obligation, <bibl>
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.
23. <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 2, 3.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What doe we make profeſſion of, and binde
our ſelves unto in Baptiſme?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Wee profeſſe our ſelves to be ſuch as
<pb facs="tcp:116554:10"/>
belong to Chriſt, beare his name, have fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
with him in his death, and reſurrection,
and binde our ſelves to walke ſutably her un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,
in dying to ſinne, and riſing to newneſſe of
life, <bibl>
                     <hi>Mat. 28. 19. Coloſ.</hi> 2. 12.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What doe wee make profeſſion of, and binde
our ſelves unto in the Lords Supper?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Wee profeſſe our continuance in that
holy fellowſhip, and binde our ſelves to walk
worthy of it, denying to have any fellowſhip
in the unfruitfull workes of darkneſſe, <bibl>1
<hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 16.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What are the inward means of applying
this Covenant?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Two; The one principall, the other
inſtrumentall.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is the principall?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Spirit of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt,
which is ſent into the hearts of ſuch as are the
children of the Covenant, and heires of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,
to convince them of their owne ſinful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
and of Gods righteouſneſſe, making
them willing to ſubmit to it, and able to cloſe
with it, <bibl>
                     <hi>Gal. 4. 6. Joh. 16. 8, 9. Pſal.</hi> 110. 13.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is the inſtrument all means of apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
this Covenant?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Faith, which is the gift of God, and
therefore given, that the ſoule may be made
<pb facs="tcp:116554:11"/>
able, to take hold of the Covenant, and be
actually poſſeſſed of the bleſſings of it, to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification,
and life, <bibl>
                     <hi>Epheſ. 2. 8. Acts</hi> 13. 28.
<hi>&amp; 15. 11. Joh.</hi> 1. 12.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What are men required to beleeve, that they
may be made partakers of Chriſt, and the bleſſings
of the Covenant?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They are to beleeve, that Chriſt came
into the world to ſave ſinners, and ſuch as are
loſt: and perceiving themſelves to be ſuch,
to looke up unto him, and to relie upon him
for ſalvation, <bibl>1 <hi>Tim. 1. 15. Eſa.</hi> 45. 22.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Are not men bound to beleeve, that Chriſt
died for them in particular?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They are bound to labour after ſuch a
particular perſwaſion, but they are juſtified
by a faith of adherence, although they have
not attained unto the faith of evidence and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Heb. 6. 11. Mat.</hi> 15. 1.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is the chiefeſt end, tbat God aimes
at in making this Covenant, and admitting ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
into it?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The praiſe of the glory of his grace,
and that Jeſus Chriſt may in all things have
the preheminence, <bibl>
                     <hi>Epheſ. 1. 6. 12. Col.</hi> 1. 18.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How is this end attained?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> By Gods enabling men to beleeve, and
ſo to ſubmit to his righteouſneſſe in Jeſus
<pb facs="tcp:116554:11"/>
Chriſt, which beleeving as it is the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of applying the Covenant, ſo is it the
maine and principall part of that obedience
which is required, and performed under this
Covenant, <bibl>
                     <hi>Rom. 10. 3, 4. Rom.</hi> 16 26.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Doth not love to God, and our neighbour,
belong to that obedience, which is to be performed
under the new Covenant?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Vndoubtedly it doth: But then wee are
to conſider, the commandement that binds to
it, as a new Commandement, <bibl>1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2. 7, 8.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Why doe you call it a new commandement?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In two regards: firſt, In regard of the
principles, in ſtrength of which it is perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med:
ſecondly, In regard of the motives
whereby it is urged.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q</hi> What are the principles?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, The Spirit of grace, and adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
which is therefore called a Spirit of
love: Secondly, Juſtifying faith, <bibl>2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 7.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What are the motives?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Gods loving us, and giving his Sonne
to dye for us, his reconciling us unto himſelfe
by the death of his Sonne, pardoning our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities,
pittying our weakneſſes; which prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples,
and motives, the Covenant of workes
takes no notice of, <bibl>
                     <hi>Epheſ. 4. 32. 1 Tim.</hi> 1. 5.
1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. 11.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:116554:12"/>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is then the difference between that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience,
which the Law required, and that which
is performed under the Goſpel?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The obedience under the Law was to
be performed by ſuch abilities, as were natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
to man; the obedience under the Goſpel,
is performed in ſtrength of a renewing Spirit,
and a juſtifying faith; the former is made up
of love, and acts of it, the latter is begun in
faith, and compleated by love; the former
was the matter of our righteouſneſſe to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification,
the latter, whether wee conſider
faith, or love, is not our righteouſneſſe, as
they are acts of dutie performed by us: The
former was to be perfect, both in parts and
degrees, or elſe not accepted; the latter if it
be univerſall, and ſincere, is accepted with
God, and that for the Covenants ſake, <bibl>
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.
16. <hi>Rom. 13. Epheſ. 1. 15. Gal. 3. 12. Gal.</hi> 3. 10.
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 6.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What workings of heart will there be in
thoſe, whom God doth bring into the bond of this
Covenant?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Such as are actually admitted into this
Covenant, will diſcover more or leſſe graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
workings towards God: Firſt, In a way
of prayer, and ſupplication: Secondly, In a
way of ſelfe-reſignation to God.</p>
               <div type="explanation">
                  <pb facs="tcp:116554:12"/>
                  <head>Explaine the former.</head>
                  <p>They will put the Covenant in ſuit, and
what they finde to be matter of Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,
ſhall be matter of their prayer; If God
promiſe to pardon iniquitie, they will pray,
to have all iniquitie taken away; if God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe
to give a new heart, they will pray, that
God will create a cleane heart, and renew a
right Spirit within them, <bibl>2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7. 27. 2
<hi>Chron. 20. 6. 9. Jere. 31. Hoſea 14. 2. Ezek.</hi> 36.
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.</bibl>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="explanation">
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfold the latter.</head>
                  <p>The ſoule perceiving by the Covenant,
which it hath imbraced, Gods bountifull
giving himſelfe, and his Chriſt to it, gives it
ſelfe backe againe to God, and comes to be
in a covenanting frame, willing to be joyned
to the Lord in an everlaſting Covenant, <bibl>2
<hi>Cor. 8. 5. Jere.</hi> 50. 5.</bibl>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="questions">
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> Doth the Covenant of the Goſpel, make
voyd the Law?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No, in no wiſe, the doctrine of faith,
and free grace, doth contrarily eſtabliſh the
Law, <bibl>
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 31.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:116554:13"/>
But the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Wee are not now nnder
the Law,</hi> 
                  <bibl>Rom. 6. 14.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Wee are not ſo under it, as to ſtand
or fall by it, in reſpect of our eternall eſtates,
not under it ſo as to ſeek righteouſneſſe to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification,
by the workes of it, not under it ſo
as to be ſubject to the curſe of it, in caſe of
ſinfull ſwervings from it; But as it is a light,
diſcovering what is good, and what is evill,
withall commanding the one, forbidding the
other, ſo are we under it, and ſtand bound to
be ordered by it, <bibl>
                     <hi>Acts 13. Gal. 3. 13. Rom.</hi> 7. 7.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What proofe can yee give hereof?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The New Teſtament doth abundantly
prove this, take onely one Text, <bibl>
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6, 2,
3.</bibl> where the Apoſtle doth urge the Law in
the very letter of it: <hi>Honour thy father and thy
mother; for this is the firſt Commandemetn with
promiſe, that it may be well with thee, and that
thou mayeſt live long on the earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> What is the ſtate of ſuch as neglect this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant
which the Goſpel holds forth?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They ſhew hereby that they are for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
in a ſtate of damnation, they deſpiſe the
riches of Gods goodneſſe, ſet light by the moſt
precious bloud of the Lord Jeſus, they neglect
the great ſalvation, and unleſſe they repent,
they will moſt aſſuredly receive the greater
<pb facs="tcp:116554:13"/>
damnation, <bibl>
                     <hi>Joh. 3. 18. Rom. 2. Heb.</hi> 2. 3.
<hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 15.</bibl>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <head>An APPENDIX, annexed
hereunto, for further illuſtration
of that which goeth before, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
the uſe of the Covenant
in a practicall way.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ODS dealing with man, is ordered
out in a way of covenanting, yet ſo
as that the Covenant of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel,
in reſpect of its outward ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration,
is ordered out with commands,
charging man with his dutie. But then wee
are ſo to conſider the dutie, as matter of a
command, as that wee alſo acknowledge it
to be the matter of promiſe, in the ſtrength
whereof it is to be performed. And herein
lyes a maine part of our ſpirituall wiſdome,
when our dutie is required of us, not to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
abilitie in our ſelves, but to bring the precept
to the promiſe, and to ſearch what there is in
<pb facs="tcp:116554:14"/>
the promiſe, and Covenant, as matter of free
conveyance, anſwering to that which the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
requires, and ſo to ſue out by prayer, the
bleſſing of the promiſe, that wee may be ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled
to performe the dutie of the precept.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Precept.</hi> It is mans duty to beleeve, <bibl>
                  <hi>Mark<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 1. 15.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Covenant.</hi> The Covenant holds forth belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
as a free gift, <bibl>
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 8.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prayer.</hi> Prayer ſues it out, <hi>Lord helpe my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beliefe,</hi>
               <bibl>Mark. 9. 24.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Precept.</hi> It is mans dutie to repent and turne
to God, <bibl>
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 30.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Covenant.</hi> The Covenant holds forth repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
as the gift of God, <bibl>
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 5. 31.
2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 25.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prayer.</hi> Prayer ſues it out, <hi>Turne thou mee,
and I ſhall be turned,</hi> 
               <bibl>Jere. 31. 18.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Precept.</hi> It is required of man, as a dutie, to
make him a new heart, <bibl>
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16. 31.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Promiſe.</hi> It is Gods promiſe, to give a new
heart, <bibl>
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36. 26.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prayer.</hi> Prayer riſes up ſutably to that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe;
<hi>Create in mee, a cleane heart, O God,
and renew a right Spirit within mee,</hi> 
               <bibl>Pſal.
51. 10.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:116554:14"/>
               <hi>Precept.</hi> It is mans dutie to love God, <bibl>
                  <hi>Mat.</hi>
22. 37.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Promiſe.</hi> It is Gods Covenant to circumciſe
the heart to love him, <bibl>
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 30. 6.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prayer.</hi> Prayer workes out in the ſtrength
thereof, <hi>That God would direct the heart, to
the love of him,</hi> 
               <bibl>2 Theſ. 3. 5.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Precept.</hi> It is mans dutie to feare God, <bibl>
                  <hi>Deut.</hi>
10. 12.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Promiſe.</hi> It is Gods promiſe to put his feare
into our hearts, <bibl>
                  <hi>Jere.</hi> 32. 40.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prayer.</hi> Prayer purſueth it, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nite my heart to
feare thy Name,</hi> 
               <bibl>Pſal. 86. 11.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Precept.</hi> It is mans dutie to waſh and be
cleane, <bibl>
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 1. 16.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Promiſe.</hi> It is Gods promiſe, to ſanctifie and
cleanſe, <bibl>
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36. 25.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prayer.</hi> It is the buſineſſe of prayer, to ſue
out this promiſe, <hi>Waſh mee, and I ſhall be
cleane,</hi> 
               <bibl>Pſal. 51. 7.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Precept.</hi> It is mans dutie to draw neare to
God, <bibl>
                  <hi>James</hi> 4. 8.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Promiſe.</hi> It is Chriſts promiſe, to draw men
unto him, <bibl>
                  <hi>John</hi> 12. 32.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prayer.</hi> Prayer riſeth up ſutably hereunto,
<hi>Draw me, and we will run after thee,</hi> 
               <bibl>Cant. 1. 4.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:116554:15"/>
               <hi>Precept.</hi> It is mans dutie to walke in Gods
Statutes, <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 4.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Promiſe.</hi> It is Gods promiſe, to enable him ſo
to doe, <bibl>
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36. 27.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>Prayer. <hi>Prayer workes up accordingly;</hi> On
that my wayes were directed to keepe thy Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes,
<bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 5.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Precept.</hi> It is mans dutie to be ſtrong in the
Lord, <bibl>
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. 10.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Promiſe.</hi> It is Gods promiſe, to make him
ſtrong, <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 29. 11.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prayer.</hi> Prayer fetcheth ſtrength from him;
<hi>Give thy ſtrength to thy ſervant,</hi> 
               <bibl>Pſal. 86. 16.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Precept.</hi> It is mans dutie, not to depart from
God, <bibl>
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. 12.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Promiſe.</hi> It is Gods promiſe to his people,
that <hi>they ſhall not depart from him,</hi> Jere. 32.
40.</p>
            <p>Prayer. <hi>Prayer anſwers hereto;</hi> Oh let me not
wander from thy Commandements, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119. 10.</p>
            <p>For thou, O Lord of hoſts, God of Iſrael, haſt
revealed to thy ſervant, ſaying, I will build thee
an houſe: therefore hath thy ſervant found in
his heart to pray this prayer unto thee, <bibl>2 <hi>Sam.</hi>
7. 27.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:116554:15"/>
BEhold here yee children of the Covenant,
and heires of promiſe, a new and living
way, conſecrated by bloud, paved with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes;
a way of ſtrength to the upright; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
they may walke from ſtrength to ſtrength,
till they appeare before God in <hi>Sion.</hi> Let no
diſcouraging thoughts, concerning the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie
of the way, which is ſet before you, poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe
your hearts, ſo as to hinder your ready
application to it, and cheerfull progreſſe in it.
A yoke you are commanded to take upon
you, but ſuch as is made moſt eaſie to beare,
becauſe that God who layeth it upon you,
hath covenanted to ſtrengthen, and ſupport
you; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e who is righteous in commanding,
is gracious in promiſing; be you ſtrong in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving,
and fervent in prayer, and your work
will be your meate, your dutie your delight.
I conclude all with the laſt words of the ſweet
<hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the man who was rayſed
up on high, and that by Gods free Covenant,
who having had experience of his own frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
and fore-apprehending the ſad changes
that ſhould after come upon his houſe, yet
<pb facs="tcp:116554:16"/>
comforted himſelfe from the conſideration
of the ſtabilitie of Gods gracious Covenant,
<bibl>2 <hi>Sam. 23. 5.</hi>
               </bibl> 
               <hi>Although my houſe be not ſo with
God</hi> (i. e.) as a morning without clouds, and
of a cleare ſhine, <hi>yet hath he made with me an
everlaſting Covenant, ordered in all things, and
ſure: for this is all my ſalvation, and all my deſire,
altbough he make it not to grow.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:116554:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
